this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Jeff Dolittle in
this episode I'll be discussing
waterfall versus agile methodologies
with Jeremy Miller jeremy is a senior
software architect at Cal Avista
software Jeremy began his software
career writing shadow IT applications to
automate his tedious engineering
documentation then wandered into
software development because it looked
like more fun
Jeremy is heavily involved in open
source dotnet development as the author
of structure map storyteller and as the
lead developer of martin jeremy
occasionally manages to write about
various software topics at jeremy D
Miller dot-com welcome to software
engineering radio Jeremy hey thanks Jeff
Lee for having me on today yeah glad
you're here so we've been talking for a
while about some projects that you've
experienced throughout your career and
you mentioned to me recently that you
spent the last year or so working on a
team using what you described as a
waterfall approach to software
development so can you start by
explaining what you mean by waterfall
and maybe how this particular project
contrasted with other projects you've
worked on sure it first of all what I
want to what I want to bring up is you
know the organization we're doing this
within it is just early in their
migration and adoption of agile
processes and practices so this is a
starting point it's not the end point
and weirdly enough I have seen a process
like this before so going all the way
back to classic waterfall I'm gonna
build up what sounds like a straw man
but folks actually do this okay so the
idea with the waterfall is that you are
able to do things in phases in a linear
fashion the idea that the metaphor of
software development as construction the
business analyst
talk to the business they go out and
they gather requirements and then they
write up a document describing all of
these requirements then they bring on
the architects the architects talk with
the BAS a little bit and they design a
technical design specification then they
hand that off to the developers and tell
the developers go build this when the
developers feel like they have it
complete or more likely when the
schedule says they're supposed to be
complete okay finally at the end of this
testers come on and test read up on the
original business requirements and they
test those requirements against what has
really been delivered the problems come
up and right off the bat is
communication communication and context
it is quite possible that the analysts
and the business were never on the
project at the same time as the testers
are not very actively on the project
same thing the developers may not have
been on overlapped much with the
business analysts or even the architect
so the information is being conveyed in
about the least efficient way possible
by dropping off documents haven't
necessarily been proven out by any kind
of feedback as an architect I know full
well that a lot of my designs early on
our best guesses and they have a
tendency to grow and adapt and change as
soon as you get into the real
development the waterfall process may
not give you a lot of chance to do that
adaptation so some of the problems you
hit shops that buy in really hard to the
idea that waterfall actually works as
soon as the VA is done delivering their
design there the requirements
documentation they'll go off and work on
a completely different project same
thing with the developers so what you
have happened is at no point are all the
people who are contributors to a project
focused on the same project at the same
time when you get into testing you start
getting bugs the developers may not
remember much about the code I face
circumstances in the last couple months
where we have had to unwind
and code that had been completed
according to us up to a year earlier
well so that that splitting context the
the lack of communication and just the
the lack of flexibility to recover from
early early mistakes for their designs
and requirements is extremely
problematic and that's what agile was
originally meant to address and change
okay so to kind of summarize some of
what I heard you say first off it
sounded very linear like it's sort of a
forward only approach and once we've
moved from one phase to another there's
sort of no going back exactly that's the
theory it never works it cannot work
like that but in theory that's how it's
supposed to work and the problem is the
shops completely build their
organizational model around the idea and
concept that waterfall actually works
and you don't go backwards right and you
also mentioned that as you get further
along in the project it sounds like key
stakeholders and decision makers are no
longer available in your experience to
possibly answer critical questions or
help may be managed through a potential
change to the project yes exactly
or even if they are they're cold on the
project it may be something they worked
on six months earlier and they just
flat-out do not remember that the
fine-grained details right or testers
and developers they're not learning
about the project at the same time so
there's a lot of potential waste when
developers and testers interpret
requirements documentation differently
hmm yeah for sure
so you mentioned construction and I know
you you sort of caveat of what you were
saying and saying that in a way you were
building up a bit of a strawman though
it's similar in your experience to
things that you've been a part of but
it's interesting because when I think of
construction it seems like typically the
architects and the contractors are
available throughout the lifecycle of
the project and there isn't sort of a
disappearance of those people from the
scene so I'm just curious as that
analogy accurate in the sense of
do waterfall projects maybe work
differently from construction projects
in that regard they work differently so
I just just ironically so I actually
have a background in construction so I
actually started as an engineer before I
got in the software so I'll give you two
I'll give you two experiences you know
one helping build a house where no the
architect was not involved okay
whatsoever
we just had plans and on the hottest
most humid July afternoon you can
possibly imagine building a roof over a
garage and getting it most of the weight
done and the the foreman of our art crew
suddenly looks really concerned looks
around and realizes the plans are just
drawn incorrectly okay so out comes the
up comes the reciprocating saw and we
have to take the roof that we just built
we have to take it down and raise it up
six to eight inches because the plans
were wrong by so there's the problem
there for software of there are things
some things that you have to be very
we'll talk about this I know a little
bit but later when we get more into the
agile side of things construction some
things have to be done correctly upfront
and decided because it's really hard to
change your mind
it hurts to build a roof and then they
have to take it down because you didn't
build a high end you didn't design a
high end that that's a negative example
on a more positive example so my first
job out of college I was an engineer
helping design and build petrochemical
plants and there was a lot of
give-and-take between even near the end
between in the engineering side and the
construction side when the construction
side would occasionally find things that
couldn't be built or just couldn't be
right not not many but some but we were
able to accommodate that because we had
a three-dimensional model of the entire
piping of the piping through the entire
plan and
he'd go and we could very accurately
model how was it gonna work in the
physical work and we could check it out
and test it out before anybody
physically tried to do that in the
software world I'm not sure we can
accurately predict how things are gonna
work Rick Lee from paper some things we
can a lot of things actually need to be
built okay so maybe part of the design
process of software it sounds like
you're saying requires some amount of
actually building to see how things will
function together whereas in some of the
engineering discipline that you
participated in in the past you were
actually able to model things prior to
actually building them yes or to drive
this home a little bit of why software
is not quite construction when I was an
engineer we use something we use
something called the boiler code that
there's a set of engineering standards
for piping pressure and all the making
things safe that code it's evolved over
time but that code trace back to I think
the 1880s okay because the basic
properties of stainless steel has never
changed and will never change they're
very well understood as a software
developer I think it's very unlikely
that you're gonna be using the exact
same set of libraries tools versions of
everything from two projects in a row
you're going to be dealing with unknown
materials all the time yeah so can you
think of a project that used a waterfall
methodology and they actually tried to
rationalize using that as their approach
in your experience I can and I'm going
back I'm going to be going back to the
early 2000s here but so going back to
the time before agile development so
part of the rationale behind a waterfall
it's really up to you some of it is at
the organizational level the idea that
we have a finite amount of resources and
resources means pass but we have a
finite number of certain types of
and rather than having some of these
specialized skill sets tied down on one
project what if we could arrange the
process in the entire 300 person
organization such that we can most
efficiently share the skill sets and
cover more of these projects and the way
we're going to do that is we're going to
rationalize suffer as kind of a
manufacturing factory line of the
business analysts are going to come on
come up with the requirements they're
going to work with the architects
they're gonna create a high-level plan
technical plan the architects is gonna
work with the technical lead and they
are going to create a detailed technical
specification and then finally the
developers can be loaned on to the
project and they will quickly build the
spec and then from there it turns over
to the testers okay so at no point do
you have to have all of these
specialized skill sets tied down on one
single project with the idea and the
hope that you can share these skill sets
kind of ripping people out to project
initiatives and try to do much more many
many many more things in parallel so the
rationale there would be that it's an
attempt to try to share resources so
there may be maybe a second big thing
you know the first was a way to share
resources and be able to paralyze
theoretically parallelized more
initiatives across their organization
the second is just kind of maybe an
older idea so folks that come from older
platforms you know especially thinking
about people that came from C++ or COBOL
or pure database development where code
was really kind of risky and hard to
change that that came up with this idea
that writing software it's kind of like
pouring concrete that you know first
need to figure out exactly what you're
doing
because if you don't get to concrete
forms exact
right you've you've completely messed up
but you build your plan of exactly what
you're gonna build so taking this
analogy farther you build the concrete
forms and then you just pour the
concrete and let it dry in you're done
with the idea that once the the concrete
is poured you can't really change its
shape so a lot of waterfall is based on
this I give that you have to know
everything upfront or you'll never be
able to get anything done right so a lot
of waterfall was based on the hope that
if you did enough diligence upfront you
know enough this is back in the days to
when you a unified modeling language was
was popular if you did enough diagrams
and enough reviews that you could weed
out the problems with the approach and
you can hand over a proven out it's set
of specifications I could just indeed
built that at that point coding was just
a mechanical exercise typing right okay
so before we move on to really get into
agile I feel like you've set a good
foundation for us for your experience
with waterfall but are there any
positive practices in waterfall that
you've seen that might be worth
emulating or is it all in your
experience needing to be replaced or
subsumed with different practices
honestly the only thing that I think
would be appropriate or really place to
be appropriate for waterfall in my
opinion are projects where budget isn't
necessarily a concern okay and the
canonical example is somebody in the
crowd is when you say but the Apollo
spacecraft software I've been waiting to
bring that up so thank you for bringing
that up yourself and that's obviously
gonna come up but they were also writing
in a way they they weren't writing a lot
of user interface stuff they didn't have
the same budget constraints that you and
I have on your projects and and I would
be very careful saying what worked for
Apollo gonna work for me
the other places so there's a little bit
of a heisting Heisenberg uncertainty
principle around software processes you
know the act of measuring progress and
controlling progress and estimation has
a tendency to slow you down but in
theory you can be more predictable
sometimes with with waterfall or you can
at least feel like you are so if like
there's some kind of regulatory aspect
to it or maybe you need like industry
auditors to come in and validate your
approach before you start that's
probably going to push you more to the
waterfall but when we start talking to
the ad ad gentle stuff the reality is
it's a spectrum and very few projects
are gonna be at either either extreme
poll right okay well that's a good segue
then for us to talk about agile in
relation to waterfall so first off when
did you first encounter the idea of
approaching a project using an agile
methodology do you remember so in the
very early 2000s I was I was in my very
first official IT job and I was very
quiz ative about the world of software
development and I started stumbling on
some books really about the old rational
unified process okay you know well some
of the very first iterative process but
shortly after that I stumbled on to some
of the initial writings about extreme
programming and it just sounded like
such a much better way to do things than
what we were attempting to do with my
hard and strict waterfall shop shortly
after that I was fortunate enough I was
able to jump straight from big IT
waterfall into a small consultancy that
was a very early adopter of extreme
program so your first experience in
particular had to do with extreme
programming which maybe explain for our
listeners what's the relation of extreme
programming to agile and what maybe
distinguishes it from other agile
methodologies sure Sochi programming was
a very early age Allah it was very
influential I know there's a few shots
that that still do it today there's
still XP clubs book clubs and meetups
but it was extremely influential before
scrum took over and pretty well wiped
everything else out the biggest
differences between extreme programming
and scrum for me is extreme programming
was quite a bit more developer centric
focused a lot more on engineering
practices then then scrum does today and
it was probably a little bit more built
on philosophy rather than having more
detailed project management structures
and structures like scrum does today but
the time it was a very vibrant community
and it just felt alive like we are
finding better ways to get software done
and in practice and I should should say
very clearly I did have some very
negative experiences with extreme
programming but in the whole it was a
much friendlier kind of environment to
work and it was much easier to get
things done okay so extreme programming
has some certain practices around it
from my understanding can you maybe
explain what a few of those are and how
they sort of fit within that that
particular methodology sure so some of
the more famous things it was some of
the first formal methods to come up the
idea of of iterations so a lot of the
philosophy the driving driver from this
was the idea that we want to work with
an evolutionary fashion so we want to be
delivering features features early but
when we delivered things we want to
deliver
there was an idea that if you wanted the
the features you were building in each
iteration to be dun dun dun meaning they
were potentially able to be released
into production so not just write code
for months and months and months and
then tests but combined all of the
phases the old traditional phases at one
time so we are as quickly as we can we
move from from analysis to coding to
testing it for just a little bit of the
system at a time and then move on
okay so iteration testing being
adaptable maybe you didn't mention this
specifically but it sounds like the
drive to get something shipped early
would be to also get customer feedback
earlier in the process and maybe be able
to turn that back into changes to the
design am i catching that correctly
absolutely so one of the killer problems
problems with waterfall is you knew much
more about how the project should have
worked at the end the some of those
other ideas that are at lay the user
feedback you got very late was it just
came too late to improve the project so
XP a really any iterative process it's
built around the idea that you learn as
you go so try to maximize your ability
to take advantage of what you learn as
you go instead of committing to what
might be the wrong plan to wrong
requirements the wrong architecture too
early but we have to follow the plan yes
okay so there's something you haven't
mentioned yet about extreme programming
which I find interesting because the
first thing I think of with extreme
programming is pair programming so in
your experience has that been an
integral part of XP or is that maybe
been over-emphasised
in my mind or others or how does that
fit in in your experience in the very
early days I love it it's been years
since I've I've done projects with a lot
of pair program but the red driver it's
maybe back up just a tiny bit into the
organization so there was an ideal as
part of extreme programming that you
wanted collective code ownership and the
real driver there was the idea that you
did not want people specializing in one
area of the code and you never wanted
one piece as much as possible you do not
want that area of the code of
chose coke that's Marco that's Sandra's
code you wanted as much as possible you
wanted developers to be able to move
between areas of the code so there were
more eyes on the code people had a
better shared understanding of how the
code is working and how we're building
so that more people could be effective
and building the system it which which
also has a little bit of a site benefit
of being more adaptable on what you can
take on if more people are able to work
in different areas of the code so a
couple questions on well I guess first
off as you're saying that it reminds me
of the book the the Phoenix project and
the guy Brent who is the bottleneck for
everything because he has all the
knowledge and the information I'm not
sure if you're familiar with that book
but I'm sure as many of our listeners
are familiar with that concept if you
have a single person who has all of the
sort of tacit knowledge in their mind
and when they're overloaded or
unavailable nothing can get done and and
it sounds like XP is trying to avoid
that kind of a that kind of a problem is
that correct
it's explicitly trying to avoid that and
pair programming was a way to do that
okay there was also the belief that pair
programming was a way of having constant
code reviews okay that to keep people
kind of on on a good path to keep people
from when you're by yourself and you're
maybe not getting a lot of feedback on
your designer approach maybe you over
complicate things sometimes having two
people it'll catch peridot catch edge
cases maybe keep oh no you can just do
it this way you don't have to do this
elaborate thing good so in a situation
like that like you're explaining with XP
it sounds like the goal is to have
people be very interchangeable but what
do you do about the fact that different
people have varying areas of expertise
or maybe specialization around
technologies or portions of the
technology stack for example database
versus algorithmic programming versus
user interface development how does that
play out in an environment like that
sure
and I'm glad you asked ask that because
that's really important it's a very
important difference between the
old-fashioned water fogs in describing
and what we have now so one of the
points of emphasis in extreme
programming that I still like ranged for
very true today the very best teams the
teams that are most productive are
self-contained teams with
multidisciplinary people that have every
skill set that is needed to deliver
their project is part of a team right so
if you think about some of the things
that make software development slow for
us it's external dependencies it's need
to have formal handoffs with other
people needing to collaborate with
people from outside of your organization
or just you and I happen to interact
with developers with completely
different skill sets so one of the
things that that that happens that can
be very problematic so right now I
occasionally have to integrate or some
of our car client projects right now
we're helping integrate some brand new
dotnet core stuff too much older dotnet
framework stuff to IBM iSeries mainframe
code the Britten and RPG so just as a as
a recent example from the last couple of
years some of the teams and projects I
work with we're helping a client
integrate some new net code with old IBM
ice series applications and we get along
we get along just fine
with the RPG developers to work on the
iSeries but we don't have a lot of words
in common it's hard for us to
communicate because I don't think either
side really understands how the other
works and it has been a real problem in
our ability to collaborate so taking
that back to just how do you deal with
how I as a front-end guy deal web
developers which that that's kind of a
joke nobody lets me do UI work but UI
developers talking to middle tier people
talking to database people so that
waterfall world those different kinds of
developers they could
sefa bleep Ian totally different teams
because you have the specs everybody
code in spec and it all works and all
combines together except that never
works in an agile process especially
within the extreme programming days you
wanted a multidisciplinary team you
wanted very close collaboration between
all these different people so maybe I
don't understand every technology but if
I'm pairing you know especially when
we're crossing the boundaries and
integrating front-end code back in as an
example if we're working together we
might have a much better chance of
getting a smoother collaboration coming
back to some of my very early days I'm
actually going all the way back to being
an engineer again building these giant
petrochemical plants it takes a lot of
different types of engineers piping
engineers pumps engineers the phrase
kinds of chemical engineers civil
engineers one of the things I had
impressed upon me very early is when
you're communicating with all these
other types of engineers you need to
understand a little bit about what they
do and how they work so that you know
best how to give them the information
they need it by understanding how
they're gonna consume what you tell them
and then on the backside if you're
understanding what they're telling you
about their work and how it impacts your
designs that that's the way to be most
effective and it's absolutely true with
software development today yeah I just
heard an interesting phrase the other
day called technical empathy and it
sounds similar to what you just
described in the engineering world where
the idea is you should have empathy for
the person who's downstream from the
information that you provide or the
api's that you publish and that
definitely improves communication
between different parties especially as
you said where maybe their knowledge
domains are disparate and distinct to
some extent I've never heard that but I
like that yeah I think that's that's
very apt so we've talked about extreme
programming and a little bit before you
and scrum and it sounds like a lot of
your experience with extreme program and
whis maybe a little further back in your
history and maybe more recently you've
experienced other projects that have run
in different ways so maybe there's other
other agile methodologies besides XP or
scrum but maybe speak to a little bit
about how you've seen the agile
landscape evolve over the last say 10
years or so well so 10 15 years ago
there were a lot of different agile
processes there was a whole family there
was extreme programming scrum something
called crystal Wright from Alice mewho
burn a lot of things yeah a lot of
things I don't even remember enable but
by and large scrum is completely won out
and most of the people that that I work
with that have joined the industry in
the last 10 years that really believe
that scrum is synonymous with agile at
this point so maybe talk about that a
little bit how what distinguishes scrum
from extreme programming are there any
shared approaches and any distinctive
approaches that separate them for one
another generation axes and what are the
cultural touchstones for me and as a
small child is watching scooby-doo on
Saturday mornings and after-school
realists and scooby-doo had had this
great model for years and then one
horrible day the new season started and
there was this new character called
scrappy-doo that changed everything and
scrappy was really annoying and it
ruined scooby-doo for millions of
Generation X kids to some degree you
know especially for those that came out
of the idealistic world of extreme
programming scrum is the scrappy-doo
event okay well if you're gonna throw
out a Gen X reference you you might need
to provide us some links so that
listeners can go and find out whose
scrappy-doo is maybe better cities that
the jar jar binks
yes that's probably more round that's
kind of an old reference to now these
days was too shocking
so okay now there may be people that are
using scrum and feeling like or maybe
even having good experience with it so
you're gonna have to unpack that a
little bit that might be a controversial
opinion oh I will but so what I need to
say is you're probably just very I have
absolutely no doubt that some folks out
there are doing very well scrum okay and
some people are running off the road so
scrum has the scrum and I should admit
scrum is actually older at leading
stream program but scrum did not become
popular until the agile development kind
of maybe craze of the early 2000s and I
think scrum took off because of the
scrum Certified Master Pro the CSM the
the kind of formal programs that you
could get for certification or in scrum
and scrum has much more focus on project
manager which i think is I think made it
very popular and palatable for manager
types and the problem was scrum not that
saying that the performative ceremonial
things in scrum the stand-ups the the
sprint planning the estimates the story
poker those things aren't necessarily
bad but what's front left behind from
extreme programming was a ton of
engineering practices and just thinking
about how do we work iteratively how do
we evolve systems without letting things
go completely off the ritz
scrum kind of take this attitude of here
are some relatively prescriptive project
management practices that you should do
and oh by the way we think you should
adopt good engineering practices that
will support this style of project
management but we're not really going to
talk about how you guys go figure
yourself so to summarize what you just
said you've experienced scrum being more
project management focused and maybe
there's been an homage paid to the need
for good engineering principles but
maybe without having a little more
prescription about the how that often
maybe falls by the wayside in terms of
importance that that's absolutely what I
have observed it is what I have also
heard from sharing experiences with
other people in the industry so maybe
give some more details about a project
you've been on where maybe you saw scrum
in the extreme and the engineering
principles that you're describing were
not included as part of the process and
what does that look like well sure the
problem isn't necessarily with what
scrum does
it's what scrum does not and the folks
that are succeeding are they're adding
this kind of thinking and process so
building scrum without a strong set of
automated testing or test-driven
development in any kind of continuous
testing practice if you're relying if
you're trying to do iterative scrum but
relying purely on manual testing or so
one of the things that I had drilled
into me in my extreme programming days
was during an iteration you try to
dribble stories out to testing as fast
as you can you do not wait until the
last day of the sprint to drop
everything on testing you got to give
your test there's a chance to keep up
with you if you're doing all the scrum
project management but you're not
thinking about how am I going to test
this how am i writing unit tests with
this am i doing continuous integration
to have constant feedback about what's
going wrong if I am NOT constantly
adapting inside of the code if I'm not
seeing taking that step back and saying
this design that we chose early on that
worked great for the things we were
building early on No
longer works we need to do something
different if you are not doing that kind
of consonant retrospective kind of
adaptation if you don't have the safety
net of the automated testing of the
continuous integration then you're gonna
drive yourself completely off the cliff
if you're doing scrum and trying to
constantly churning out new new things
every two three weeks or whatever it is
right so you mentioned engineering
discipline before and now you mentioned
a few what are commonly called and
software architecture that the illah T's
right I heard a couple of those come out
you mentioned flexibility you mentioned
adaptability are there other factors
maybe that need to be considered up
front you sort of moving away from the
the scrum things it kind of sounds like
you could you could pick on it all day
even though you did concede that it it
certainly does work for some people as
long as it's not sort of scrum in a
vacuum right without these other things
but maybe in terms of enabling agility
it sounds like it's not just about not
thinking or not planning right but it's
it's about certain ways of thinking so
maybe what are some of those things that
have helped you be successful with the
methodologies you followed sure so I
want to back up and we're gonna go in a
little more of a philosophy so there was
an idea it came from well I know it from
Kent back but I think it's been stated
by other people this idea that you do
the simplest thing that can possibly
work and that that's a loaded phrase
it's a loaded idea because what's simple
to me and to you and to our other
listeners may be completely different
things based on what we all know but
inside of a given time this idea there's
an idea in from extreme programming that
I should not try to design ahead for
things that we do not need at this this
point I should not introduce any kind of
fancy caching until we have a
demonstrated need to do some kind of
extreme performance requirements I
should not try to design in flexibility
just in case somebody
wants to come back and do it a little
bit differently or add similar functions
so there's a related concept that's a
say and it horrified me a couple years
ago when I realized that the developers
I was working with were very familiar
with scrum project management but had
never heard this so there's a phrase
called Gagnon you aren't gonna need it
so the idea that I do not build any kind
of infrastructure in right now that I
don't need for the features that we are
delivering right now so let's unpack
that a little bit because that that's
gonna be kind of problematic so in a
positive way gagney allows me to
concentrate on solving the problems I'm
I need to solve right now to ignore a
lot of other problems that I may face in
the upcoming future at the distant
future and by reducing the number of
things I have to judge with my own mind
I'm probably able to be a lot more
productive right it is generally going
to be easier there's a value judgment
here to that it is going to be easier to
change simple code if it needs to be
more complicated later than it is to
work with complicated code so that makes
it makes it easier for us to focus
there's kind of then there's an obvious
problem of what what if you need it
later
right so with extreme programming one of
the things things we learn and this
applies perfectly well the scrum or any
really any process we need to take a lot
of investment in making our code easy to
change so if we're gonna delay
infrastructure if we're gonna focus on
just to hear it now but there is a later
we are going to add some of these things
later when we need them so one of the
priorities one of the things that was
most important about succeeding with
extreme programming is you needed to
make it both easy and safe to change
your code layer there was a concept
called reversibility of can I change my
mind
can I take an easy approach now but
opted into a more complicated before
approach later so with that investment
in how do I make my code easier easier
or safer to change a lot of that was
based on the idea of feedback so and
this is where things like test-driven
development
behavior driven development where you
use business acceptance tests on more
automated tests continuous integration a
lot more project automation that gives
you a lot of automated regression
testing cycles so that it is now much
safer and less risky to change and
modify your code and that there's a lot
of discipline to it but that discipline
allows you to evolve a code base over
time and that's what enables you to keep
working in a narrative cycle without
drowning in technical debt problems and
I guess from what you just said that
kind of counter balances that idea of
you aren't gonna need it the yagna it's
there are things that you are going to
need and you just describe what some of
those are from your experience if you
want to have reversibility as a
characteristic of the system you're
designing then there's certain things
you need to do to enable that and yet if
somebody's just running around yelling
yaga yaga Agni but then they're not
really helping you accomplish those
things so what what do you need up front
what are the things in your experience
that you really can't compromise on
because I could imagine somebody saying
to you maybe who doesn't have the
experience or has different experience
well we don't need all of those things
you've just described we don't need BDD
testing for the business or we don't
need you know fill in the blank how do
you kind of navigate those kinds of
decisions upfront when you're beginning
a new project well it's not so much
those specific practices sure but what
you really need you really need are good
feedback loops and the faster you know
that you did something wrong or just a
theory about how things are going to
work the faster you know that that is
wrong or right you can proceed to either
fixing it change
or just moving on to the next thing okay
so the most important thing and there
are different ways to go about it but
the most important thing is to have a
really good feet and informative and
quick feedback cycles to let you know
I'm on the right track or I'm not on the
right track and I need to adapt
okay so adaptability and you mentioned
reversibility so do you think there's a
general consensus on what makes a team
agile or not and if not why not or if so
why I don't think I would worry too much
about the definitions
quite so much or who is real agile if we
had this discussion ten years ago I
would have given you a very different
answer I would say you have to be doing
test-driven among you have to be doing
continuous integration you should
probably be doing pair programming even
though I hate doing pair programming but
it's good for you I don't think I would
go prescriptive but I wouldn't worry
about what's real or not but pay
attention to what is and isn't working
and taking an attitude of constant
adjustment and that means that the team
doing the work needs to be both kind of
alert to their own circumstances they
need to be constantly thinking about
what is working what isn't working what
they could change and then your team
needs to be empowered to go make those
adjustments themselves you know we
talked about some of the ways that scrum
can go off of course I think one of the
most common ways that scrum fails is
when scrum is used to micromanage
developers throw testers when they're
not giving you a lot of leeway in how
they approach the work or being able to
stop or change their even the way
they're doing estimates or requirements
if the team is not empowered to change
they never change and they probably stop
thinking about how they do things and I
think that's when the serious problems
creep in right and now we're just doing
whatever the whatever keeps the
pointy-haired boss off of our case
right at that point yes and the plenty
here boss
he may have he or she may have been a
great developer a project manager or
something in the past but they don't
feel the friction the pain points that
you do because they're not part of it
they don't have a great inside knowledge
of what what's slowing you down or what
helps you all the time they're not the
ones who can most accurately adapt the
process or the requirements or the
technology so let's say I'm a developer
or an engineer and I'm working on a team
and whether it's as you mentioned before
there's no complete waterfall there's no
perfect agile but there's this spectrum
in here but maybe I have a sense that
there's something that we could do
differently or better how have you
experienced ways to overcome resistance
maybe to others who either don't see
what you see or disagree or maybe want
to say well that's not agile or that's
waterfall or this kind of thing how in
your experience have you navigated that
form of resistance maybe to some ideas
you've had about what you felt would
improve process live in Texas now but I
grew up in Missouri so the state motto
is you got to show me
mm-hmm so it may be a case of you need
to demonstrate what you want to do
differently sometimes you can get away
with with white a little bit of
whiteboarding session but you may have
to prototype type something romantic
eight you know here's how we could do
requirements we can capture requirements
differently and make it concrete to some
day and some degree I mean there are
conflicts and especially in a flatter
flatter team like a jello encourages I
think it's really important you have to
learn to compromise sometimes you need
especially with the team full of several
alpha type personalities you got to slow
down and let yourself listen to the
other ideas give other people's ideas a
chance let them speak and sometimes you
need to willingly lose an hour
hmmm why is that important because some
things there are times when someone else
is a good solution is good enough and it
might also be people understand things
differently there may be an approach
that you see that looks perfect to you
and maybe it is but other people don't
understand it in to some degree you need
to get along with your co-workers and
when there are times of it may just be I
prefer to name variables like this but
the other three of you prefer to do it
that way try to pay attention to what
things are really important and be
self-aware about what things are just
preference or arbitrary and be a little
easier on things that you don't that you
know really aren't that important and
then you can also take that active well
let's just okay let's try your approach
first but let's also then have an
agreement of how do we judge whether
this is successful or not so we can come
back and reevaluate this decision
immediately after yeah so being willing
to compromise be flexible prioritizing
what really matters and not making
everything the most important battle to
wage but I appreciate that last thing
you said about inviting people to
creatively think about how we can
measure the success of a particular
decision I think that measurability
definitely speaks to the idea that we
want to be we want to be agile right and
not just do things in a way that
somebody told us is something called
agile absolutely so let's see what are
some ways in your experience that you
can actually use agile methodologies to
help inform your technology choices oh
that's a good question so I can think of
a couple of couple of things it's
looking at through the lens that this
idea we talked about a little earlier
called reversibility my ability to
change my mind
can I pick pick a technology where I can
evolve the system easily so taking the
example I'm gonna pick on working with
relational databases okay versus
a project that Jeff and I an open-source
project Jeff and I worked on together
called Martin that is instead of
doctorate identities if I'm working with
a relational database
I do incur a little bit of friction
there is a little bit of impetus to get
the data model up front because there's
a little bit of overhead of oh I really
need to model it this way and if I need
to model it this way instead I have to
change database tables and database
scripts and make corresponding changes
in my code if I add a field if I had a
new property to a model object I may
need to go add some from the database a
database mapping or in and then come up
to my code I have a little bit of a
wormhole anti-pattern
there's just mechanical things going on
and there's it gives me some reason to
resist wanting to change the code and
try to get things a little more perfect
up front taking a different approach if
instead we use the document database so
doctor the database a little bit
schema-less but really the database
schema is inferred from the middle tier
code in impact inside of an agile
process what that allows me to do is
it's much much simpler for me to change
and kind of evolve my models models
because I don't have to do a lot of work
to keep the database structure in line I
may not even have to rebuild the
database I mean you'll just change my
middle tier code and just get so that
kind of reversibility it is a very big
deal my ability to evolve and not have
to be perfect up front is a lot better
with the document database versus a
relational database ignoring as an
example I say yeah you're you're
referring there to what I've heard
classically referred to as the impedance
mismatch meaning we have these different
models of our system and they don't
necessarily easily map to one another
and it sounds like what you're
describing there is a case where perhaps
if you use certain document database
technologies that can reduce not
eliminate but reduce that impedance
mismatch and maybe help with the
stability that you're looking for very
much so in that that's a big deal so
here's another example in some web
technologies and most I'm thinking
mostly older older web technologies it
was very difficult to retrofit security
or validation in because everything
happened in the same log of of code you
know thinking about how awful for us
being a dinette developer how awful web
forms was where everything had to be
done together right thinking way ahead
now in the world of asp.net core I can
very cleanly in my application code I
can focus on business logic or data
access and completely ignore security
requirements at that time because I can
always come back and layer in some kind
of middleware to add security around my
code without changing my code you know
an example of Robert Martin's old
open-closed principle but I have a lot
of reversibility that I can retrofit
security either authentication or
authorization by adding these clean
wrappers would that have been modified
my existent code so that enables me to
to worry about one a few things at a
time and evolve the system that does
imply that upfront you have to make some
technological decisions that allow for
that kind of approach so in that sense
you know maybe it's an HTTP pipelining
model or something of that nature so
there's there's not just enabling
technologies but maybe even enabling
patterns that allow you to be more agile
and more reversible in your choices oh
absolutely
so reversible reversible technologies
technologies that allow us to be more
easily testable because automating
testing is such an important feedback
cycle to enable the work in an agile way
that absolutely the the desire for
reversibility testability just the
ability to change your mind all of those
inform my technology choices and pattern
choices up front so yes there is there
is some upfront thinking but that
upfront thinking is is really informed
by what is going to make it easier to
adapt and evolve over time okay
so you've mentioned before that one of
your goals and some of the projects you
worked on previously was to try to get
features delivered quickly and just by
definition delivering features means
delivering functional requirements but
how do you capture and make sure that
non-functional requirements aren't being
neglected things like quality things
like performance of the system
scalability of the system how do how do
those various non-functional
requirements play into an agile type
methodology so performance the
scalability can still well to some
degree performance and scalability it's
still understanding patterns patterns
are just just technology structures the
first order effect is still just us as
individuals how much we know about the
platform we're on the patterns to make
the communication mechanisms just
understanding the problem to me that's
still the first order effect
process and practices is second order
effect so we could talk to Angela all
day but you still you still need to know
your stuff on the technology front but
scalability and performance or two
things that can't be measured if they
are requirements that are important
enough to justify the investment you can
set up you can set up automated testing
to measure performance thresholds or
scalability thresholds as part of your
continuous integration pipeline right
such effort your continuous will arrange
such that are at the very least invest
in project automation so that your
performance or scalability load testings
are repeatable so that you can very
quickly or relatively easily run those
you ever meet right
so reversibility repeatability
and being able to make some decisions
upfront that will allow you to have
those characteristics seems like that's
pretty important yes so you've mentioned
your background as an engineer and my
understanding is one fundamental
principle of engineering is you you want
complex things to depend more on simple
things and not the other way around and
it seems to me that based on a principle
like that it'd be pretty important to
know sort of somewhat upfront what are
going to be the the more stable parts of
your system that you can rely on and
what are the more in stable part or
unstable parts of your system so how do
you make those kinds of decisions up
front or maybe earlier in your process
so that you're depending on good
abstractions that you can rely on
because if those things change further
down it could really be disruptive to
your system completely agree with the
prints okay so I would still prioritize
having really good feedback cycles and
very good automated testing coverage
rather than trying to get basic
abstractions right up front I think it's
developers I think we have a tendency to
grow up wrong
one of the most common ways for us to go
very very wrong
is building abstraction to early but
before we know a lot of things I think I
think it is better to delay introducing
or blocking into especially restrictive
abstractions until you get later in the
project but let me throw let me throw a
big wrinkle into that because I think
I've been more aligned with the premise
of what you asked five and ten years ago
one thing that is that is I think is
different now in a very positive way
versus just a very few years ago I think
it is much cheaper more just
mechanically easier to do integration
testing today than it was thinking about
things like trying to do a full
integration
your website of the stack all the way
from an HTTP request to the database
that was a very expensive proposition
ten years ago in terms of manpower to
make that happen right today I think
that is much simpler the introduction of
docker to quickly spin up isolated
databases you technologies all kinds of
little things for us being net
developers now that we have Kestrel that
like every other platform we finally
have a web server that can run in
process so that you can inside your test
harness you can spin up your entire
application and run HT requests through
it and measure the database changes the
database all in one go I think that has
actually changed the way that I approach
design such that I am less likely to
bring on abstractions for the sake of
promoting undoing figured votes
depth ability or evolved ability and my
system right that I don't think I need
to I don't need to complicate the code
with all these extra scenes that we used
to introduce to be able to put mock
objects in for automated unit testing I
would forego that and I would depend
much more on integration tests on the
outside end then I would have ten years
ago but I say that because I think the
technology has changed the equation so
much now that integration testing is
much cheaper easier and much more
reliable that used to be ten years ago
yeah and in a way I mean I I might call
that blackbox testing in the sense that
it's opaque you know what you're in
flows oh you know what you're in flows
are rather and you have a sense of what
you desire out flows to be and so what's
happening behind the scenes is sort of
hidden from you and you're able to test
it at a different level but you could
you could also argue that that is an
abstraction it's just maybe a higher
level abstraction that it's easier to
flex with when things change in your
requirements I think that's a good way
of putting it fine grained abstraction
especially if you're guessing out who
can hurt you absolutely when you do make
abstractions you need to be careful what
you're generalizing yep but that that's
a that's a very long discussion by
itself yeah that's good that's good
engineering practice right there right
yeah so maybe it's just a mechanism to
get their folks on really old old
original concepts of encapsulation and
coupling right trying to hide the
details of how the sausage is made
underneath the sausage casing that you
just don't leak leak a lot of details
give me a concrete example or a project
I did a year or two ago working with a
web service that was a facade over a
third party product that web service
still leaked a lot of implementation
details that were particularly in
particular to the third party system
such that even though you were using the
web service you still hadn't know a lot
about that third party product behind it
to do engine I thought you were really
doing is saying I want some load
information or I want to approve this
loan right you weren't you weren't able
to express that in terms of the
semantics of what you were trying to
achieve you had to still speak for third
party language to begin were doing right
it's interesting you brought up the idea
of encapsulation and information hiding
and there's an article that I'll link to
in the show notes by a gentleman named
David Parnas who isn't really well-known
but he was actually the inventor of the
concept of encapsulation and it was
controversial 40 years ago when he
invented it I'm not sure if you've heard
of him before I'm curious no okay well
then you can also be enlightened when I
post the link to on the criteria to be
used for composing system modules it's
it's literally the seminal paper on the
idea of encapsulation and and
information hiding but that's a great
point there that a good abstraction is
going to shield you from those kind of
things but obviously point taken on the
danger of making the wrong abstraction
or prematurely abstract that would
definitely fly in the face of making you
agile
yeah it's not it would but and also to
to other things if you're being agile
you constantly adapt as soon as you
realize an abstract you're working
around an abstraction that the
abstraction is hurting you or you're
down casting you just you to change the
abstraction your distraction no longer
works right it's very possible that it
worked in for the early features and
that later things break it so you got to
change the abstraction rather than
trying to plunge ahead then the second
point and I don't think this is specific
to agile but when you're creating your
abstractions
it's very frequently valuable to create
it by pulling what you need out of the
client so one of the old the old
mechanisms for designing low-level API
is is you actually build a client first
yeah as necessary
you mock er stub fake implementation
just to define from the side of the
client of what it eats rather than
trying to build the API upfront with
kind of that that build it and they will
come kind of mentality hmm yeah well
this has been a helpful discussion I
think and enlightening for me as well in
some ways so I'm curious if listeners
want to learn more about effective
software development methodologies where
do you think they should get started
so I'm gonna wonder that's a little bit
so even though it's really old I would
still recommend grabbing a copy or you
could probably find a library kid backs
original white look you see if I could
find what the name is but the original
extreme programming book from there I
would find an author named Martin Fowler
and I would try to find his book just
called refactoring and I know there's a
recent update that's out there okay well
is there anything else we might have
missed that you'd like to mention in the
time we have left
I'm sure I will think of tons of things
tomorrow but I think it's absolutely
worth worth reading up a little bit more
some best practices of designing for
testability I think is a big thing okay
and I think it's really really important
don't just depend on a separate dev ops
team to understand how all the project
automation works just so the developer
make sure you understand the bill would
test tools that you're working with and
try and make sure you understand how the
people around you a little bit more
about how they do their own jobs okay so
if people want to find out more about
what you're up to where can they find
you on the Internet so it's
unfortunately not as technical as it
used to be but still active on Twitter
geremy D Miller on Twitter but as much
as I try to blog
I am also Jeremy D Miller comm you'll
find blog posts a lot of old art
articles
probably a link to this podcast for
posts and I'm very active on github with
with a lot of different projects okay
great so shout out to people who want to
get some open source contribution cred
they can go join up on some of those
projects and send in a PR absolutely
love getting pull requests okay well
Jeremy thank you so much for this
discussion about waterfall versus agile
well thanks for inviting you Jeff this
is fun awesome well this is Jeff
Doolittle for software engineering radio
thanks for listening thanks for
listening to Nessie radio an educational
program brought to you by out your
police software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at SE - radio net to
provide feedback you can comment on each
episode on the website or reach us on
LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our
slack channel at SC radio slack calm
you can also email us a team at SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening